as news outlets all around the world
continue to publish articles about the
upcoming great recession and the fact
that the s p index has dropped almost 21
percent year to date should we as
investors be concerned with our current
strategy of dollar cost averaging into
the s p 500 index in this video we're
going to be looking at this question and
whether it's a good idea and what are
the risks so what is the s p 500 well
essentially the s p 500 is just a market
tracking index of the top 500 companies
that are listed on the us stock
exchanges this approximates to about 80
percent of the market capitalization of
all u.s listed companies according to sp
global the s p 500 index was created in
making it the first u.s market cap
weighted stock market index as of the
31st of december 2020 sp global
estimates that there is approximately
5.4 trillion us dollars that's invested
globally into products that actually
track this index there are over
165 index listed products listed on the
s p global website alone although the s
p 500 index was officially launched in
1957 the valuation goes back all the way
to the 3rd of january 1928 but it's
important that you understand before
this is only a hypothetical back-tested
index and therefore it's not actual
performance of you the u.s 500 top
listed companies but instead based on an
index methodology that was actually
established at the time of listing this
index now one of the products that's
actually listed on the sp global website
as tracking the s p 500 index is the spy
now the spy or spider s p 500 etf trust
was the first etf listed in the us
according to state street global
division launched in january 1993. now
the fund objective is like all other
funds that track the s p 500 index so
this instrument's main goal is to
provide exposure to the price and then
the yield performance of the s p 500
index before expenses according to
statista as of the 21st of june 2022 the
spy is the largest market etf in the
world by assets under management with
approximately
336 billion us dollars under management
but despite being well diversified
across a number of industries and the
fact that this index is actually built
from the top forming companies within
those industries in the us during
periods of economic distress and
uncertainty the s p index and related
etfs can and will go down substantially
this happens as businesses and analysts
across the financial industry
re-evaluate and re-estimate their cost
basis going forward and therefore their
cash flows and growth prospects into the
future now one of the most common pieces
of advice i see around the internet for
people of our generation is that we
should be doing dollar cost averaging
into the s p 500 into a market tracking
index even warren buffett recommends
this strategy to investors who don't
want to devote the time to do their own
business analysis so i really wanted to
question this general knowledge and
actually instead of looking for papers
on the internet telling me that it's the
best thing to do possibly for passive
investing i wanted to go through the
numbers and look at the historical s p
500 index create a synthetic spy
like investment product and then
consider a 25-year holding period for
different age individuals looking for
retirement over that period we're then
going to look at all the results and
judge whether lump sump investing or
dollar cost averaging is better and what
the risks are associated with each of
those strategies so to kick things off
let's look at the performance of
investing in the spy etf over the last
25 years two individuals one is a 25
year old in july 1997 who comes into 300
000 us dollars now he is going to lump
sum invest into the spy the other 25
year old at the same time only has 10
dollars to his name however he's just
begun working saving and plans to invest
1 000 us dollars per month on the first
trading day of the month in the spy etf
now we're going to be quite harsh on
these individuals every trade they make
we're going to make the assumption that
they're paying 10 in brokerage fees
which is uh very conservative we're also
going to make the unrealistic assumption
that they're able to buy on the closing
price on that particular trading day now
we're going to track both of these
strategies through to today at when
they're 50 years old and see how they've
done over the last 25 years now
unsurprisingly the 25 year old who came
into hundred thousand dollars and
invested in the spy
has done extremely well he has just
under 1.24 million dollars at the end of
the term with a total return of
924 000
in comparison the person who's been
dolocos averaging finishes up at the age
of 50 with 772 000 for a gross return of
000 although they have made a positive
return there are periods where they had
contributed more money than the value of
those current uh spy etf shares and this
is important to remember that despite
being short-term fluctuations that over
the long term in both of these scenarios
we have actually got a positive result
with quite a good annualised return now
if we consider this in terms of gross
percentages the lump sum investor
received a 313
gross return while the dollar cost
averaging investor received 157
return this is slightly unfair because
really the person who was working and
contributing 1 000 every month did not
have that capital to invest at the time
so what we actually need to consider is
what was the fund value return for that
particular investment now calculating
the fund value return methodology is
simply just with respect to the cash
flows and the actual number of units of
the underlying so for example when the
first investor buys x amount of shares
in with one thousand dollars and then
comes back into the market and buys
another y units of shares then all
you're doing is you're accounting for
the time differences between those two
investments to get a weighted average
cost of capital for your total units of
share consider it this way essentially
each time you're buying x units of
shares you're buying it for a certain
price and those units make it all the
way to the end of maturity if you hold
on to them and the return for that
particular investment over that time
period is calculated then you then come
back into the market in one month time
and then you buy x units of shares or y
units of shares it could be different
for a different price and now you need
to consider how many units of y shares
returns over that time period all the
way until your holding period and then
you do this continually for the next 25
years so the fund value return takes
into all these cash flow considerations
and extra units of shares into
consideration now when you look at the
fund value return of this second
investor who dollar cost averaged in
essentially he gets and converges to on
the money that he's invested the actual
percentage return that the lump sum
investor got into and that is 312.5
now it's not exactly because of course
there is time in differences and
inefficiencies over the long run now for
both the lump sum investor and the
dollar cost average investor their then
adjusted annual return equates to about
5.84 so now what happens if you weren't
25 and started investing dollar cost
averaging into the market in july 1997.
what happens if instead you were 25 in
june 1997 or what happens if you were in
uh 25 and you wanted to invest over the
next 25 years in the january
1928. so we're going to look at all the
permutations of a person who comes to
the age of 25 begins working and then
investing 1 000 dollar cost averaging
into the market for the next 25 years
we're then going to compare that to the
lump sum investor who comes into 300 000
and we're going to look at the results
so the number of 25-year periods that we
have for a person who starts investing
at a particular month from january 1928
all the way through to today would
actually only be
833 and again that's with the last date
that you could have invested is in july
1997 to get that 25 year holding period
to today so let's now consider those 833
scenarios and look at the distributions
and the returns so now going through the
assumptions that we have related to
creating a synthetic etf going back all
the way through
to 1929. the first is that we can
actually buy for the closing price on a
particular day which is complete bogus
but it's going to do for this analysis
two we have no fees and or management
fees connected with this etf so no
expenses now this is somewhat netted off
by our next assumption which is that we
do not take dividends from these
investments over time and obviously etfs
do incorporate the dividends that they
get from the 500 companies within the
etf now this is the important one the
synthetic etf is
holding the one tenth of the value of
the index and this is in line with how
the spy index and etf is created now the
other assumption we're making is that
we're not going to be adjusting for
inflation these are going to be nominal
values so now i'm going to show you the
gross returns between the two strategies
now the first thing that i want you to
notice is that on the y-axis of both of
these plots i am showing you the gross
total returns as a dollar figure and i
want you to notice the sheer difference
between these blue bars over time from
one strategy to the other i also want to
make it clear that this is the 25 year
holding period where uh it's recorded at
the end so the investor is 50 years old
and you realize your p l and that is
where the bar is shown now the second
thing that i really want you to notice
is that there are negative returns in
the lump sum
investment strategy now these are
occurring in january 1929 and then also
when you started investing in september
1929 now these were the real high points
before the great depression hit in the
united states now the great depression
was from 1929 through to 1933 but
obviously the economy didn't really
recover until after world war ii during
this time period unemployment rose to 25
and the gross domestic product the gdp
of the usa decreased by 30 now other
than starting at these two individual
points in terms of months for your lump
sump investing essentially with both
strategies in any other month period you
would have had a positive return over
your 25 year holding period now looking
at the distributions let's look at the
lum sump distribution and what i want
you to realize is that it's highly
volatile with a minimum of minus ten
thousand dollar return over a 25 year
period all the way up to 5.9 million
dollars but historically over time we
can see that the absolute gross return
of the lump sum investing strategy with
90 confidence intervals are between 470
000 to 3.2 million now this is with a
median return of 1.4 million and a mean
return of
1.56 million now let's compare this to
dca which we can obviously see never
produce negative returns we have a max
of 1.99 million nearly 2 million and a
minimum of 96 000
we can say with 90
confidence that over this given strategy
that the dca approach is between
160 000
to up to a gross return of 1.4 million
dollars this is with a median of 560 000
and a mean of 610 000. now let's talk
about the risk essentially what happens
in the worst five percent of cases i
want to know what my expectation is the
mean of the five percent worst cases in
both scenarios so in the five percent
worst cases for the lump sum essentially
this would equate to a hundred and
eighty thousand dollars whereas in the
dca strategy these five percent uh worst
case outcomes would be on average a
hundred and thirty thousand dollars now
this is amazing to see that even in such
low probability odds of this investing
strategy that over time you'll still
expect in five percent worse cases to
receive quite a positive return on top
of your 300 000 worth of invested
capital over time now lastly we're just
going to compare the annualized returns
for all these different scenarios now
you obviously hear that everyone says
hey look the s p 500 is going up at
seven percent over time but that's the
line and that's for the lump sump
investing what about for the dollar cost
averaging approach well essentially the
dollar cost averaging annualized returns
when considered as the fund value return
approach considering when the cash flows
happen and the returns are those
individual investments over time when
you consider those annualized returns
you
you eventually converge upon the lump
sum
distribution as you can see here and
essentially we can say with 90
confidence interval that the annualized
returns of both of these strategies are
between
3.85 to 10.3 percent with a median of
7.2 percent and a mean of 7.07 so i
think this has been an important
analysis because what we've seen is that
over a 25-year holding period using a
lump sum approach has actually in the
past would have returned a negative
gross return however using the dollar
cost averaging approach what you do is
you space your capital out over time and
you would have averaged in at lower
points although we never saw negative
returns in our 25-year holding periods
from 1928 onwards what i will say is
that the distribution was a lot tighter
and a lot smaller in terms of gross
returns for dollar cost averaging
compared to lump sum lump sum did have a
very large upside with a noticeably
larger median value and that's why in
general you have heard the investing
approach that when you do have a large
sum of cash it's better just to be in
the game rather than not this is not
investment advice but i think what we
can establish from this that obviously
over time you were not guaranteed a
seven percent return whether you were
lump sum investing or dollar cost
averaging into the s p 500 etf or index
tracking funds with that being said if
you liked the video please give it a
thumbs up subscribe to the channel and
leave a comment in the section below i'd
love to hear your thoughts about the
analysis or similar analysis that you've
done